Некоторые называют это ультрадистансом, некоторые экстремальный спортом, ну а мне просто нравится
долгие заезды на велосипеде. Правда я не знаю на самом деле, что значит "долгие".
Я думаю, это очень субъективно, мне нравится видеть, как пейзажи меняются вокруг меня.
Что мне действительно нравится в велосипеде, это то, что
он доступен, что позволяет добраться быстро до места, что он всегда под рукой,
будь это повседневный двухчасовой заезд после работы,
будь это прогулка за мороженым с друзьями, или поездка в другую страну.
В нем так много аспектов.
А также еще много мелочей.
Можно крутить с минимальным усилием, катясь как волна,
и это похоже на полет
или когда вы давите изо всех сил, пытаясь обогнать друзей.
В общем, есть огромное количество моментов, которые делают езду на велосипеде веселым занятием.
Куча разных вариантов,
едете ли вы гонку и доводите себя до предела
за несколько часов, или вы пытаетесь пересечь несколько границ в течение нескольких дней.
Я думаю, что разный опыт это действительно круто.
Я никогда не назвала бы свои заезды тренировками,
потому что для меня тренировка это всегда строгий план, и она не должна быть веселой.
Конечно, я как-то тренируюсь,
потому что готовлюсь к гонкам.
Но я тренируюсь так, чтобы это было весело.
Я еще поняла, что мой настрой всегда сильно связан с моим физическим состоянием.
Если я чувствую, что готова проехать 200 км, то я обычно действительно могу сделать это хорошо.
Если мне хочется максимально быстро проехать короткую дистанцию, все тоже проходит хорошо.
И если мне вообще не хочется ехать, то я думаю, что это также правильно для тела в данный момент.
Таким образом у меня выходит получать удовольствие и не терять мотивации.
Велосипед для меня не просто что-то, что мне нравится, это также важный инструмент чтобы сосредоточиться.
Чтобы заменить им что-то разрушающее.
В некотором смысле, я могу работать со своим телом, и развиваться вместе с ним,
и это не только социально приемлемо, но и также очень полезно и весело.
That's why cycling is an important part of me, maybe, I don't know, to my personality sounds very cheesy,
but yes, it's somehow a part of me.
For me there was never a real starting point to my cycling because cycling has always been a part of our family.
I can remember getting my first bike, then I had one that looked like a tiger duck,
then I had a cherry bike and so it went on and on and cycling was always there.
My dad is a cycling fanatic himself, so we always watched the Tour de France at home and the Giro and so on.
It was always part of family life
and so it was pretty normal that we often went on long tours
where I think other parents would have said "God, what are you doing with your children?".
In a race in which you plan the route yourself, as is now the case with Dead Ends & Dolci, you can of course get lost in route planning.
I do all of my route planning with komoot, whether I'm going on a ride at the weekend or for a race like this.
The Dead Ends & Dolci is a race with five dead ends.
The start and finish is in Bellinzona and these dead ends are spread around Bellinzona in virtually every direction.
I think all five are on some kind of summit or at least a climb and at every dead end there is a dolci, meaning some kind of dessert.
Whoever has eaten all of them first and gets back to the finish, is the winner.
For me personally, and that's why I do these races, I want to get the most out of myself as possible. So I want to do this as well as I can.
I definitely want to feel physically exhausted at the end but not destroyed, I want to feel healthy and happy
and still somehow strong at the finish line, but knowing that I did it as good as I could have possibly done.
I want to be at the finish knowing I used all the grit I had.
There are many ways to tackle this adventure: my challenge is to connect these checkpoints as fast as possible and get back to the finish
and that's why I will be on the road for about 500 km and 9000 meters of elevation which I find exactly the distance and elevation that you can do in one day.
That's kind of the appeal of maybe doing it in 24 hours, which is ambitious. Actually I don't know if I can do it but I know it's theoretically possible.
When it comes to the Dead Ends, I don't worry too much about food. There are "dolci" at every checkpoint and you can carry enough food on you for the 24 hours that it's actually enough.
I'm going to cook potatoes and take them with me and then lots of gummy bears and chocolate. You can pack in so much that I think it will be enough for the race time.
In general, not just in the races, it has simply become my motto that I don't forbid myself anything, also in everyday life, if I feel like doing something and if I feel like eating a whole bar of chocolate, then I do it.
I think that's just a little bit due to my past and I'm definitely not going to deny myself anything during a race.
...Frosting is the best thing about cheesecake.
You could have also written Frosting with cake.
Yes. Actually all I need is the frosting.
And a carrot to go with it. For dipping.
At the start of the race there is always a very special atmosphere. There is such a tension in the air and you can tell that everyone, even the toughest people,
also if I know them well, is a bit nervous and asks questions or adjusts something on the bike.
Everyone is talking about what the weather is going to be like and you just notice that there is something in the air.
When you set off, what I like most is when I'm alone for the first time and have this expectation of what's going to happen and I think that's the coolest feeling during a race.
It's a mixture of respect, I wouldn't say fear but definitely respect.
There is also a bit of curiosity about what is going to happen but also a great joy that you don't have to do anything else except ride your bike,
and the good feeling of being able to show that you have prepared and being able to give it your all right now.
[Music]
In everyday life it's mostly about functioning somehow, maintaining social relationships, with colleagues and so on.
In everyday life, you are this tough, friendly and, best of all, good-humored person.
On the bike, especially with yourself, you don't have to please anyone or, I don't know, you can just be happy with yourself.
And then that thin skin that you get when you ride a bike for a very long time, that supports it. So I feel very liberated, not just where I'm going, but also emotionally.
[Music]
This is a help for the riders, so they can find the correct route
and don't get lost in the wilderness.
That's why we've painted this little signpost on the road.
Is there coffee? Or tea?
Where is the Dolci?
Ahhh
Jana Kesenheimer? Exactly.
I've already marked you. I thought you were coming soon.
Is that yours? Yes. Uh. Thanks. Good.
Don't stress.
Ciao.
I now realized in retrospect that this probably happened to several people because the section where you turn into the castle is too short and the navigation,
If you don't look at it at that exact moment, simply continues without you having ridden into the castle.
And it also happened to me. In any case, I rode the course and then about three quarters of the way through I noticed: there were photos of a castle somewhere, at what time is it actually coming?
Then I looked at the map quickly and saw that I already passed it. Otherwise, I rode the course correctly. .
Then I briefly thought about whether I should go back on the same direction, including the castle, or whether I should take the route as planned
and then basically catch up on the castle. I took a quick look at the rules and the rules stated: every part of the course must be in the route and the direction doesn't matter.
So I decided that I would go back and "catch up" with the castle and then continue my route. I found out two or three others did it the same way as I did.
So it calmed me down a bit because that mistake kept me quite busy in my head, because route finding isn't a big strength of mine.
It's a bit of ME-time.
I'm happy to make these decisions on my own, to ride my bike just for myself. Of course I'm happy when I meet someone along the road,
but even then we usually ride together for a very short time and I personally think that's a good thing. I like to be alone and it is also a conscious decision to start these races solo.
I actually admire the pairs where it works well. I imagine this would be quite difficult for me. For me and maybe for the other person as well.
It would be easier for me if I were the weaker part. Then I wouldn't have to make any compromises in terms of performance.
It would be harder for me if I started with someone who was worse, because in a race like this, where I start to ride as well as I can, I wouldn't be able to achieve that goal.
Ahh, the climb was pretty hectic.
Great work! Have you ridden through the snow?
That's the question I ask everyone who comes up here.
Like you've been here forever... [laugh]
It's like a bag of coke.
There wasn't a smaller zipper bag, right?
Enjoy!
They get nice and warm on the back too, right?
Yes, perfect!
There's "Dolci" down there.
Yes, but you have to go down quite a bit and then up again.
Is it much? I do not know.
That's where the guy on the gravel bike turned off.
Oh well, you probably haven't seen him.
I think it was exactly where this piece of gravel started.
I mean at 8800 meters of elevation it doesn't matter anymore.
Yes, if you have signed up for Dead Ends & Dolci...
Ah, I thinks it was pretty hard work coming up here.
See you soon.
See you soon!
[Music]
Oh cool, This will definitely mean "Dolci" at the end. Right?
What?
These are letters.
Ahhh... Martin, I hope you got it.
I felt really fit the whole time, really good, and then halfway up here I suddenly had a terrible stomach ache
then I stopped briefly. I don't know.
That was definitely the worst moment so far.
It was also just incredibly steep.
[Music]
It takes about two or three hours until I feel like I've arrived and then cycling works a little by itself and you look around or maybe have little encounters with other people
or just realize how nature changes, how the time of day changes. Things happen in the environment which you wouldn't otherwise notice in your everyday life.
You focus on the present moment and on the problems that are important at the moment, I think that's special.
You no longer think about everyday life, let alone the race situation or anything else, but are just so focused on the present moment.
For example, in the Pyrenees last fall, there were wild horses and I stopped to take a photo and one of these horses came up to me
and nudged me, it was just so magically cheesy, exactly as it sounds, that's how it was. I just started crying because it was so beautiful.
That is one of these special moments which are rare in everyday life.
[Music]
I think I'm just an extremely strong-willed person. Well, it kind of started with me being a crybaby and I think my parents,
had a bit of trouble with me because I was probably a very emotional and strong-willed baby.
Then unfortunately I had a time in my youth that was very destructive. I did well at school, had lots of friends, and felt very comfortable.
I've always done sports which felt great.
At some point, my family gave up sweets for Lent
and unfortunately this became my new craze, so to speak. I started not eating sweets anymore, which eventually ended in two years of anorexia.
It was an extremely educational and also a very difficult time for me.
How should I say...
I found a way out of it, more or less on my own,
and I'm actually pretty proud of it to this day.
I think it shaped me and made me the person I am today.
I was trying to do something (my diet) perfectly
but I realized that paying extreme attention to your diet is anything but perfect.
At least in that situation. It was definitely the wrong challenge.
It shaped me until I was 18 and after that I was looking for absolute freedom, because of course not eating anything restricts you extremely.
And I was obviously very good at not eating. Thank God I managed to eat again and then I partied and went out a lot.
I lived in this realm of freedom for two or three years and used every bit of freedom that I had and took it to the extreme.
But the sport was always part of my life. Even during this party time, I always went running and ran marathons and stuff.
But I was also awake all night long in Berlin clubs and bars.
This was also an important time for me, I think.
But I then realized that sport was a way to feel myself and push my limits in a way that was not only socially accepted,
but also in a way that was good and healthy for me personally.
In a way that is not harmimg my body by partying, drinking and sleep deprivation or by not eating anything.
But rather by simply reaching for my limits in sport and exercise in such a way that it is healthy and in a social way training together with friends.
I think that's how I've managed to use cycling for myself in such a way that I can embrace this personality that I carry with me...
I used to think maybe this was a bad thing,
always having to take things to the extreme, or that I really enjoy to push the limits,
but today I actually see something extremely positive in it.
[Music]
This is the penultimate climb,
And also the penultimate checkpoint.
I now have ridden 349 km and 7007 meters of altitude.
That means there are still 1800 meters of altitude to go.
Yes.
I went to pee twice and my pants have a magnet in the back, which is really cool because you can go pee really quickly but then I couldn't reach it anymore.
I probably swore and stood there for 20 minutes.
Certainly no woman came up with this design, really.
I feel a bit of pain in my right knee, where I had inflammation last year.
But I think it's justifiable.
I think I eat a bit too little, but I also felt sick twice today.
I don't think I can eat "Dolci" at all right now.
I feel more like potatoes.
I have two more.
Wow, so beautiful!
Hi.
You have a great setup.
Yes.
I was bike-packing here in February
and then I already knew that I will be coming to this location
And I thought: "Oh God, the volunteers who are getting dropped off here." [Laughter]
Hey cool.
Thanks.
One more.
Yes.
Ah and now I have a problem.
Wow, I still have so much food left.
Yes, I have the same problem.
I need to try something salty now.
They have tea if you want.
Ciao. Ciao-Ciao. Bye.
See you later Max. - See you later.
In a race, I set off at night and it's cold, it's dark, you're really focused on the three to four meters in front of you.
The focus area is very small, just the light beam of the lamp.
It is very quiet and there is hardly any traffic. I like riding bike at night
and despite it there is still a certain tension in your body.
[Music]
Is this the last one?
Yes.
I am sure it means “Dulci”.
- I would say "Dölci".
Well, I already felt worse today.
Do you fancy an apple strudel?
Yeah...
wait, I still have the "Dolci" from the last checkpoint.
[laughter]
I'll eat that first.
Now I just need to ride home.
68 kilometers, yes
and another 800 meters in altitude.
At 5 o'clock the radar is definitely showing rain.
And I think the nausea I've experienced
was due to the fact that I didn't drink enough.
Do you take turns sleeping?
Yes.
Yes, we'll go to bed right now.
Ciao.
For me it's just the greatest satisfaction.
It's not really euphoric or anything like that,
I'm just happy with myself when I've given it my all.
It just feels good, not really too good or whatever, no rush or anything like that, but I'm just happy.
How are you?
Good.
I really wanted to finish within 24 hours.
Did you?
Yes.
Amazing. Great.
Twenty minutes to 6 o´clock I thought: Oh fuck, now I have to...
Yes hey, you still get the most important stamp of all.
Ah yes.
Ah, there's another one.
Yep, the best.
Wow.
Do you like it with cake or without?
I can´t. [Laughter]
But do you like soup? Or a beer? Or a coke? Or a bed?
Do you really have a soup? That would be great.
Just under 24 hours...
is really fast compared to last year.
but well, there was the rain.
At some point it felt like:
I'll be happy when it's over
but now at the end it went really quickly again.
At the last checkpoint I thought: Wow, this will probably take another three hours,
but then it went quickly.
I had some liquor with me, just in case...
[laughter]
Yes, I still have some. A whole pack of M&Ms.
Yes, then you can drive again tomorrow.
Yes, I think they'll get eaten soon.
Okay, I'll lie down.
I think it's really nice to spend time at the finish
to greet everyone else who arrives and to be able to feel a little bit of these arrivals.
The emotions that are part of it are nice to see.
So actually quite a lot of people send me questions on Instagram
and a lot of questions, focus on:
how do you train or how do you motivate yourself to get on the bike again and again and how do you manage to get on the bike even in bad weather?
I don't know, it maybe sounds really stupid but,
The question somehow doesn't arise for me.
I'm just always psyched.